<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The conclusion of the Earle of Straffords defence, the twelfth of April, 1641</title>
            <author>Strafford, Thomas Wentworth, Earl of, 1593-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61713</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5784C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222430</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833608</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833608</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38086</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61713)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38086)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2218:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The conclusion of the Earle of Straffords defence, the twelfth of April, 1641</title>
                  <author>Strafford, Thomas Wentworth, Earl of, 1593-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>This edition has "Conclusion .. April," in title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Guildhall Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Strafford, Thomas Wentworth, --  Earl of, 1593-1641 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Trials (Treason) --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Treason --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38086:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38086:1"/>
            <p>THE CONCLUSION OF THE EARLE OF STRAFFORDS DEFENCE <hi>The twelfth of April,</hi> 1641.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1641.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38086:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38086:2"/>
            <head>The Concluſion of the Earle of <hi>Straffords</hi> Defence, the twelfth of April. 1641.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y <hi>Lords,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>there yet remaines ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Treaſon, that I ſhould bee guilty of; the indeavouring to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the fundamentall Lawes of the Land, that they ſhould now bee Treaſon, together, that is not Treaſon in any one part of Treaſon accumulative, that ſo when all will not do, it is woven up with others, it ſhould ſeeme very ſtrange.</p>
            <p>Under favour, my <hi>Lords,</hi> I doe not conceive that there is either Statute-Law, nor Common-law, that doth declare the endeavouring to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the fundamentall Lawes to be high Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>For neither <hi>Statute-law,</hi> nor <hi>Common-law</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that ever I could hear of, declareth it ſo.</p>
            <p>And yet I have been diligent to enquire, (as I beleeve you thinke it doth concerne me to do.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is hard to be queſtioned for life and honour, upon a Law that cannot be ſhowne.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:38086:3"/>
            <p> There is a rule which I have learned from Sir <hi>Edward Cooke, De non apparentibus &amp; non exiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus eadem ratio,</hi> (Jeſu) where hath this fyre laine all this while, ſo many hundreds of yeares without any ſmoke to diſcover it, till it thus burſt forth to conſume me, and my children ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream hard in my opinion, that puniſhment ſhould preceed promulgation, of a Law puniſhed by a Law, ſubſequent to the Acts done?</p>
            <p>Take it into your conſiderations, for certainly it is now better to be under no law at all but the will of men, then to conforme our ſelves under the protection of a law as we think, and then be puniſhed for a crime that doth preceed that law, what man can be ſafe, if that be once admitted?</p>
            <p>My <hi>Lords,</hi> it is hard in another reſpect, that there ſhould be no token ſet upon this offence, by which we ſhould know it, no admonition by which we ſhould be aware of it.</p>
            <p>If a man paſſe down the <hi>Thames</hi> in a Boat, and it be ſplit upon an anchor, and a Boye, being ſet as a token that there is an anchor there, <hi>that party that owes the anchor, by the Maritime Lawes, ſhall give ſatisfaction for the dammage done; but if it were marked out, I muſt come upon mine owne perill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now where is the marke upon this crime, where is the token that this is high Treaſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:38086:3"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>If it be under water and not above water, no hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane providence can availe nor prevent my deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lay aſide all humane wiſedome, and let us reſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wil divine Revelation, if you condemne before you forewarne of the danger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh my <hi>Lords,</hi> may your Lordſhips bee pleaſed to give that regard unto the Peerage of <hi>England,</hi> as never to ſuffer our ſelves to be put on thoſe <hi>nice</hi> points, upon ſuch conſtructive interpretations, and theſe are vvhere Lawes are not cleare or knowne, if there muſt be a tryall of wits, I doe moſt humbly beſeech you, the ſubject and matter may be in ſome what elſe, then the lives and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of Peers.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Lords,</hi> we finde that in the Primitive times, in the progreſſion of the plain Doctrine of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; they brought the books of curious arts, and burned them. And ſo likewiſe as I do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, it will be wiſedome and providence in your Lordſhipes, for your poſterity, and the whole Kingdome, to caſt from you into the fire theſe bloudy and moſt myſterious volumes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive and Arbitrary Treaſon; and to betake your ſelves to the plain Letter of the Lavv and Statute, that tellethus where the crime is, And by telling what is, and what is not, ſhevves hovv to avoid it. And let us not be ambitious, to bee more vviſe and learned in the killing Arts, then our forefathers were.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:38086:4"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>It is now full</hi> 200 <hi>and</hi> 40 <hi>yeares, ſince ever any man was touched for this alleaged cryme (to this height) before my ſelf, we have lived happily to our ſelves at home, and we have lived gloriouſly to the world abroad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us reſt contented with that which our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers left us, and not awake thoſe ſleepy <hi>Lyons</hi> to our own deſtructions; by taking up a few muſty records that have layen ſo many ages by the walls, quite forgotten and neglected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May your Lordſhips be Nobly pleaſed, to adde that to thoſe other misfortunes befallen me for my ſinnes, not for my Treaſons; that a precedent ſhould not bee derived from me of that diſadvantage (as this will be in the conſequent to the whole Kingdome) I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you ſeriouſly to conſider it, and let not my par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular caſe be ſo looked on as you do; though you wound me in my intereſt in the Common-wealth, and therefore thoſe Gentlemen ſay, that they ſpeak for the Common-wealth, yet in this particular I indeed ſpeake for it, and the inconveniences and miſchiefes that will heavily fall upon us; for as it is in the</hi> 1. <hi>of</hi> Henry <hi>the fourth, no man will after know what to do, or ſay, for fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Do not put (my Lords) ſo great difficulties upon the Miniſters of ſtate, that men of wiſedome, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and vertue, may not with chearfulneſſe and ſafety, be imployed for the publike, if you weigh and meaſure them by grains and ſcruples, the publike af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the Kingdome will be laid waſte, &amp; no man</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:38086:4"/> 
               <hi>will meddle with them, that hath honours, iſſues, or any fortunes to loſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My <hi>Lords,</hi> I have now troubled you, longer then I ſhould have done, were it not for the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of thoſe dear pledges, a Saint in heaven hath left me; I ſhould be loath my <hi>Lords,</hi> (there hee ſtopped.)</p>
            <p>What I forfeit for my ſelfe it is nothing, but that my indiſcretion ſhould forfeit for my childe, i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> even woundeth me deep to the very ſoul.</p>
            <p>You will pardon my infirmity, ſomething I ſhould have ſaid, but I am not able, (and ſighed) therefore let it paſſe.</p>
            <p>And now my <hi>Lords,</hi> I have been by the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ngs of Almighty God taught, that the afflictions of this life preſent, are not to be compared to the eternall weight of glory that ſhall be revealed to us hereafter.</p>
            <p>And ſo, my <hi>Lords,</hi> even ſo with tranquility of minde, I do ſubmit my ſelf freely and clearly to your Lordſhips judgements; and whether that righteous judgement ſhall be to life or death.</p>
            <closer>Te Deum laudamus, te Dominum confitemur.</closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
